<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Professor Diab&#39;s Summaries</title>
    <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Professor Diab&#39;s Summaries</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/1.-actus_reus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/1.-actus_reus/</guid>
      <description>Summary of law on Actus Reus #  General points on actus reus: #  The actus reus can be defined as &amp;ldquo;a physically voluntary act or omission.&amp;rdquo;
For an offence to be committed, the actus reus and mens rea must be concurrent&amp;mdash;on the principle that if not, courts would punish either conduct without fault or guilty intent not expressed in guilty action.
The actus reus of an offence must be carried out voluntarily and can include the failure to act.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/2.-mens_rea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/2.-mens_rea/</guid>
      <description>Summary of law on Mens Rea #  General points on mens rea: #  There is no single kind or level of fault that applies to all criminal or regulatory offences.
The Supreme Court has held that it is a principle of fundamental justice under section 7 of the Charter that a person should not be convicted of a criminal offence without the Crown having to prove a fault element, and one that is proportionate to the gravity of the offence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/3.-participation_offences/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/3.-participation_offences/</guid>
      <description>Summary of Participation offences #  Overview #  This summary includes:
1. Counselling
2. Conspiracy
3. Attempts
4. Parties
5. Accessory After the Fact
6. Final Points
 1. Counselling: #  Section 22(1) makes a person a party to an offence where they counsel a person to commit an act that is an offence, and that person commits it.
Section 22(2) makes a person a party to an offence where they counsel a person to commit an act that is an offence and the person commits another offence that was reasonably foreseeable from the act counselled.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/4.-homicide/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/4.-homicide/</guid>
      <description>Summary of Homicide #  General points: #  Section 222 of the Criminal Code defines homicide as directly or indirectly causing the death of a human being. The Code sets out four forms of homicide: non-culpable, murder, manslaughter or infanticide.
Section 234 states &amp;ldquo;culpable homicide that is not murder or infanticide is manslaughter.&amp;rdquo;
Infanticide functions as both an offence (mother killing baby when still suffering post-partum effects) and a partial defence to murder (lowering murder to manslaughter).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/5.-provocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/5.-provocation/</guid>
      <description>Summary of Provocation #  General points: #  Section 232(1) states: &amp;ldquo;Culpable homicide that otherwise would be murder may be reduced to manslaughter if the person who committed it did so in the heat of passion caused by sudden provocation.&amp;rdquo;
Section 232(2) defines provocation as follows: &amp;ldquo;Conduct of the victim that would constitute an indictable offence under this Act that is punishable by five or more years of imprisonment and that is of such a nature as to be sufficient to deprive an ordinary person of the power of self-control is provocation for the purposes of this section, if the accused acted on it on the sudden and before there was time for their passion to cool.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/6.-self-defence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/6.-self-defence/</guid>
      <description>Summary of Self-Defence #  General points: #  The self-defence provisions in section 34 of the Code function as a full defence (resulting in acquittal) to any offence committed with the purpose of defending or protecting oneself or another from the use or threat of force, if the act committed in defence is reasonable in the circumstances.
Elements of the defence in s 34(1)
-the accused reasonably believes that force, or a threat of force, is being used/made against her or another;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/7.-mental_disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/7.-mental_disorder/</guid>
      <description>Summary of Mental Disorder #  Overview #  Distinguish the following procedural facets:
  Fitness to stand trial
  Mental disorder defence (at trial)
  Review Board dispositions
  1. Fitness to stand trial: #  The accused, the Crown, or the court on its own motion may raise the issue of the accused&amp;rsquo;s fitness to stand trial at any time during a prosecution before the verdict is rendered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/8.-necessity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/8.-necessity/</guid>
      <description>Summary of Necessity #  General Points #  The defence of necessity excuses criminal conduct (resulting in an acquittal) where an accused facing &amp;ldquo;clear and imminent peril&amp;rdquo; acts to avoid a greater harm &amp;ndash; rendering their conduct &amp;ldquo;morally involuntary.&amp;rdquo; The Court in Perka recognized the defence at common law; it applies to all criminal offences, possibly including murder. (Latimer)
Before the defence may be put to a jury, the accused must raise an air of reality with respect to each element of the defence; the burden then shifts to the Crown to prove BARD that one or more elements do not apply.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/9.-duress/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/9.-duress/</guid>
      <description>Summary of Duress #  General Points #  The defence of duress excuses a person (resulting in an acquittal) for a criminal act they commit when threatened or compelled by another person.
Duress may apply:
i. as a defence available under s 17 of the Code to a principal offender who commits the offence;
ii. as a defence available at common law to a party to an offence; or</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/presumptions__burdens/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/presumptions__burdens/</guid>
      <description>Summary of Presumptions, Burdens, and Reasonable Doubt #  i. Presumptions and burdens #  Where the Crown proves fact A, a presumption permits the court to presume fact B. In many cases, fact B is an element of an offence that is difficult for the Crown to prove but flows logically from proof of fact A.
Most presumptions are rebuttable, some are irrebuttable.
Among the class of rebuttable presumptions, we distinguish between evidentiary legal presumptions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/sentencing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://betterworklfow.net/sum/docs/substantive_topics/sentencing/</guid>
      <description>Sentencing #  General Points #  Before sentencing, counsel will:
  Ascertain the range of sentence by looking at the penalty provisions in the Code or statute;
  Decide on a sentence to recommend (kind and quantum of time, money)
  Seek to support the recommendation by citing purposes and principles in Code or statute.
   1. Kind and range of sentence #  Code provisions will indicate whether an offence is strictly summary or indictable, or hybrid.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
