<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Criminal Law Summaries</title>
    <link>https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Criminal Law Summaries</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/1.arrest_and_detention/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/1.arrest_and_detention/</guid>
      <description>Arrest and Detention Summary #  General points #  Section 9 of the Charter guarantees everyone a right &amp;ldquo;not to be arbitrarily detained or imprisoned.&amp;rdquo;
The Supreme Court in R v Le held that in order to be valid under section 9, a detention must be &amp;ldquo;authorized by law; the authorizing law itself must not be arbitrary; and, the manner in which the detention is carried out must be reasonable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/2.search_and_seizure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/2.search_and_seizure/</guid>
      <description>Search and Seizure Summary #  Preliminary points: #  Content and purpose of section 8 #  Section 8 of the Charter states:
&amp;ldquo;[e]veryone has the right to be secure against unreasonable search or seizure.&amp;rdquo;
 In Hunter v Southam Inc, the Supreme Court held that the purpose of section 8 is to protect a person&amp;rsquo;s right to a &amp;ldquo;reasonable expectation of privacy&amp;rdquo; (REP).
When is section 8 engaged? #  A person&amp;rsquo;s rights under section 8 are only engaged when: (a) a state agent conducts</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/3.wiretap_and_surveillance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/3.wiretap_and_surveillance/</guid>
      <description>Overview of Wiretap and Electronic Surveillance #  Preliminary points #  The Supreme Court held in Duarte and Wong that where police record a private conversation, they carry out a search. Part VI of the Code contains an extensive scheme for authorizing surveillance by state agents, though there are provisions in other parts of the Code allowing for other forms of surveillance or electronic monitoring (discussed below).
Part VI of the Code has three features.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/4.confessions_rule_right_to_silence_and_right_to_counsel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/4.confessions_rule_right_to_silence_and_right_to_counsel/</guid>
      <description>Confessions Summary #  Preliminary Considerations: #  An accused may challenge the admissibility of a statement made to police in three ways (depending on the circumstances):
(a) under the common law Confessions Rule, on the basis of a reasonable doubt about its voluntariness;
(b) under the Charter: as a breach of the right to silence (s. 7), the right to counsel (s. 10(b)), the right against self-incrimination or against compelled testimony (ss 11(c), 13); and/or</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/5.exclusion_under_242/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://robertdiab.ca/sum/docs/procedural_topics/5.exclusion_under_242/</guid>
      <description>Summary of Exclusion Under 24(2) #  Where an accused establishes that a Charter right has been breached in the course of an investigation or prosecution, section 24(2) of the Charter allows for the exclusion of the evidence obtained as a consequence of the breach.
Section 24(2) states: &amp;ldquo;Where&amp;hellip;a court concludes that evidence was obtained in a manner that infringed or denied any rights or freedoms guaranteed by this Charter, the evidence shall be excluded if it is established that, having regard to all the circumstances, the admission of it in the proceedings would bring the administration of justice into disrepute.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
